[SPEAKER_00]: One other point I wanted to clarify.
[SPEAKER_00]: I read this already, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way as everything has to be a... somehow include within one or more of the pañcupādānakhandhā, then in the same way, every determination, saṅkhara, must also be one or more of the pañcupādānakhandhā.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, obviously, to me, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: If everything is within the pañca-jñātanda, the determinations are within everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the same thing, when, when it said, uh, I think the Dalai Sutta, it said, well, what are the saṅkharas?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's just these five aggregates again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just things bound together.
[SPEAKER_00]: They depend, and it, because these things are bound together, because intentions are bound with, with the arisen phenomena on a, on a particular level,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's already saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, when you intentionally intend the given intentions, that's what your volition is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why volition comes also under the same sort of umbrella kind of nature of saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's bound with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: With whatever possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the difference between an arahant and putujana, in terms of these structural sankaras and sankaras in general, would be the directionality of those sankaras.
[SPEAKER_00]: For a putujana, they would be revolving around the center, which is his self or his conceit, and they would be either directed towards, or away, or both, or neither, but it would have implication of that mind and that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: For an arahant, it just wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a footnote to the passage
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think it's pretty straightforward.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically just explaining how cetanā, or negative, gives the example of a sheet of paper, which, at least in that utilitarian level, makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: I like when he says, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: The positive thing's existence is asserted by the negative in the very act of denying it, just as atheism, which exists as denial of theism, is evidence that theism exists.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, take that principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Take the principle of assertion of the positive through the denial that comes from the negative up to the very fundamental level where a thing appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't have to think about any further significance that is developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just have
[SPEAKER_00]: Form is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, there is already that division, already that sort of denial of that form by the consciousness, which is the whole result.
[SPEAKER_00]: The manifestation is the whole result of that relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is not that form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, that form is able to appear as that form.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, form in itself
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not need consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, we can't talk about appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, we have the appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from appearance, you can sort of reverse-engineer and realize the relationship that's necessary for that appearance to be, or have a direct insight into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why consciousness is to be understood, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that, that the very principle, like, atheism confirms theism, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a very, very proliferated, sort of,
[SPEAKER_00]: Example of the same principle whereby just appearance already means denial of that which has appeared to be the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a sort of a separation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't want to say, oh, it's denial of it by consciousness, because then consciousness becomes another thing that denies everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because consciousness is defined by that which is not it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense that it is possible to be it, because it's not that consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why consciousness is the fundamental negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the fundamental saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why consciousness, that's where conceit is rooted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is that which points at the self, through that basic, most fundamental division, denial, or creation, creating of a, of a, oh, this appears, this appears, this, which is different from me, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't say, consciousness doesn't say, there is me, but it kind of indicates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is different then,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you fill the blank.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, neat, because I'm always here, and all these things are changing, and appearing, and disappearing, but I stay the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it was that most fundamental kind of affirmation of the positive through its denial of its own identity, so to speak, by the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The consciousness indicates that then there is a
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it generates the power of the indication of that self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you go back to those things and the way they're determined
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you see that, oh, it is just an indication.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as such, it's positive in itself as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not as positive as thing that's being denied in its appearance, but certainly positive because you can think about it, you can discern it, you can recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as such, you drain the power away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is this?
[SPEAKER_01]: The indication you're referring to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for me, things appear for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: On top of that, the things appear for you, they can appear to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this can be mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of that, all the basic kind of very fundamental conceit is indicated by the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through that same principle of, as he described it, the negative, through this sort of denial,
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the sameness, like, oh, I'm not that which appears for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It starts indicating that you are something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am not that which appears for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you don't even have to think that explicitly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, I have to say it somehow, but it kind of would precede even the designation of the words.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is the mental attitude of when something has arisen, it's a separate thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can understand that on, I think, a gross level for the whole, like, subject-object dichotomy.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's natural attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... the thing is that the subject originates from that basic kind of indication.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just... just like a pointer that's created by consciousness by the denial of the thing that you are conscious of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just the natural experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Matter juxtaposed to consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The result is manifestation of the fall.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the conceivings that Moolaparihāsuta talks about, for example, they would fall under that kind of subtle, that directionality, or just pointing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They wouldn't be the actual fully fledged development.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's because of that pointing, that channeling, that kind of ushering,
[SPEAKER_00]: With ignorance, you just carry on further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, obviously, it's with the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's with the direction that everything is made out to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's absolutely no reason for you to start doubting that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until much later, obviously, when you're dissatisfied with the nature of existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I think, you come across the dhamma, and it says, yeah, you have to go against that grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to the point whereby, in seeing, there is only the seeing in her.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to the point when it manifested, there is only the manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no more indicated assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, rather, indication is... it perceives the assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because it indicates at something, you start assuming that something's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, you stop seeing the indication, because assumption takes over.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a matter of something being indicated, but it doesn't necessarily mean that what is being indicated is necessarily, so to say, real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it is real as an indication, but that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's not known as such, there is already a degree of... well, just by having lack of knowledge in regard to that indication, that's all it takes for that indication to be fully manufacturing a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you feed that manufacturing, you feed that result through not understanding it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it takes.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to make any other mistakes or do something wrong on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just for not understanding it, you're actually feeling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're understanding, basically, this positive-negative relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, at a very, very fundamental point of consciousness and matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The principle remains the same there, and it's just the same principle that kind of grows further and further and further, and to all of the... to, like, even intentionality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The usage of certain objects for various different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those various different things are all product of that kind of secondary indication of you being conscious of that thing at the fundamental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're conscious of the arisen object, arisen shape, arisen need, intentionality will be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I have a need to bang a hammer into the wall,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I would look for something that would fulfill that need, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And based on my experience, something sturdy, something that can take that nail into the wall.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't break under it, it won't get punctured.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if I can't find anything, I'll start kind of going even wider.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I might use the back of this metal cup.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or I might find a stone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not ideal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not perfectly tailored for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it can serve the purpose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of that does not necessarily... well, not necessarily... it does not require a sense of self, but it's on the same level of that kind of intentionality of things, the negative sort of thoughts in regard to things, the usage, the possibility in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the same level that there is also a particular intention that it's for me, it involves me, it's apart from me, it's in me, it's outside me, it's... it's in relation to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that relation can be kind of, well,
[SPEAKER_00]: It can go any way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what it is, as long as it implies you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you remove you...
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yeah, you can still use a hammer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arhant can go and bang the nails into the wall if he needs it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, he won't be like puzzled, you know, like a primate sort of picking up a tool and looking at it like there's nothing to do with it, because he lost all the concept.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All he has lost is the appropriation of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has lost the conceit.
[SPEAKER_00]: He has lost that pointing, that indication, gratuitous indication of that center independent of anything else, that sort of centering it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because center cannot be known if there is nothing
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There just wouldn't be a center.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, center starts believing that it's independent of everything and nothing and all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Peripheral is nothing to do with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the center.
[SPEAKER_00]: But how can you have that center if there are no peripheral things?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the same, like, people think things are mine because I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's completely the other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: You first assume they're yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you generate the sense I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, on top of that, you fully develop view.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely independent of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you just start appropriating more things and taking that as a... at a face value, as a complete kind of basis of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, we talked about that before, in terms of sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is like central, in a way, and people take it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of mirrors the similar relationship, and then you just... it's effortless to assume... to assume the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway, last time we had that discussion about... well, we started with, like, talking about how atheism, by denying theism, asserts the existence of theism.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just had a bunch of different thoughts that kind of came out from me, trying to think about that some more, all at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: We basically, if I understood correctly, asserted that
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, this idea of the negative denying the positive is like a necessary structural feature.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's how things can be positively manifested at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: There has to be that which is non-manifested there, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes, people might sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Not be able to understand that quite clearly, because you you kind of start with all the negative possibilities of the present thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, the present thing is what's what's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: The actual thing feels what's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossibility seems optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once you start looking at the nature of possibilities, that kind of negative, like not this, then you realize that it extends all the way down to the presence of that thing, which is what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, this is actually more fundamental than the actual thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the manifold possibilities that structurally perceive the actual thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're simultaneously present, but they're actually perceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's basically where all these thoughts kind of start, trying to understand how that, why that is absolutely necessary, and then further, eh... trying to understand, think about that whole thing we talked about with indicating.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is generated by this duality, so to say, and there were just a few things that came out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I kind of had this thought that when we have this positive indication, like indicating this is for me, that I am not that which is for me,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's this kind of assumption that myself is behind even what that is, that the negative being indicated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there's a negative, but then there's me behind that, like, in terms of, like, a directional kind of way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I was also thinking, like, sometimes it feels as though, like, self
[SPEAKER_01]: As a phenomenon, it can almost, in a way, be positive and negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that's what we're going to talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, obviously, it's the ultimate negative, but, at the same time, it's the... it's kind of the center of your universe.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it also has a positive dimension.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you were to look at it positively, it's as you would say, through fingers.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... there's nothing positive there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, there is a very
[SPEAKER_00]: Very strong positive sense of that of that self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's the thing you said, like, for me, it feels like it's even behind the negative possibility that it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in order to kind of bring it back in, and actually, that very thing you just said, it feels behind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the assumption of Aturvāda, that there is a
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how it is translated, the belief of... belief in self?
[SPEAKER_00]: Belief in self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's a common translation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's where that belief, basically, is founded upon the assumption of... a notion that yourself is completely external to your experience as a whole, that it's an outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that stems from that very more subtle assumption of, for me, also being behind
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that are for me, ultimately, even behind the negative possibilities that actually determine it, as for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you end up assuming it, that you are not within that picture, that that for me is independent of it, which is why it's particular, has its peculiar nature, which is why, obviously, the whole pādi-tsaṁpāda exists completely, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, because of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: On a subtle level, for me, notion, then there, when it comes down to the whole self-view, that's also assumed behind and everywhere below and above.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, experience as a whole, however big or small can be, self is outside of it, or it can be outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, and that's, that's nothing other than an aṭṭhā, aṭṭhārādhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you would, you would kind of reel that back in, not by sort of, you can't sort of catch it, because automatically,
[SPEAKER_00]: The way you look already implies that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your look carries the distortion, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, within that, you can you can start looking as a... no matter what's behind, no matter how ambiguous the background is, it's always going to share the nature of the negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, no matter how far behind yourself is, and you don't doubt that it's behind, you don't have to doubt that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you have to know that behind still shares the, like, the phenomenon of behind,
[SPEAKER_00]: still shares the same nature of the negative that we were talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you realize, well, it can be as behind as it wants to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can never escape the nature of a negative, which means it's within the negative.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you stop assuming, then, consequently, the existence of a self independent of this body and mind and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just... it becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems to me, kind of, like, recognizing that, for me, is, in fact, an intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of, like, any intention, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although, a special character.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see it as an actual, sort of, intention-intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if intention involves you, but, yeah, it is like any other intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the intention that points at
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems also like, so long as that is assumed, it kind of bleeds into every other intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I look at the cup and I say, that could be used for drinking for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That could be thrown.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say that that particular intention ends up being superimposed over any other intention, or the entire plane of intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's exactly, you can appropriate anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking also about that thing that Jñānavīra says, where the patuja assumes, things are mine because I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, the ārya sees properly, I am because things are mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: We touched upon that briefly last time, but I wanted to try and discuss it a little bit more at length.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically saying that those positive or somewhat positive indications are generated, in this way of speaking, not like emanating, but in terms of the structural feature with ignorance, by this denial by the negative consciousness and
[SPEAKER_01]: From then, you take those indications, which are inter... overlaid over just the normal, you know, saying, oh, this is positive, this is negative, but then there's that assumption superimposed, so to say, on them that says, oh, well, this indication of negative is the indication of myself, which is the point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... it's... what I just... we just spoke before this, basically, because
[SPEAKER_00]: There is that assumption of, for me, being behind or independent of any other intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up assuming the fully-blown self, personality, completely independent of everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the thing is, that is your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't start with a corruption of consciousness and then the developing of the particular intention.
[SPEAKER_00]: For me, that's misunderstood, that it results in a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start with a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through the sense of self, then, you can start seeing these assumptions, mistaken notions.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the ignorance doesn't have the manifested beginning, whereby this is how it originated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although it's true what you said, it won't necessarily lead you to the required knowledge, if it's not seen in the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the right order is actually to start with that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, know that for as long as this sense of self is now present, simultaneously exists, means I'm taking things to be mine, while this sense of self is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you don't... you... it's not... you're not kind of reverse... you're not kind of reversing in your sense of an explanation, but more like... that sense of self remains intact, but then your knowledge
[SPEAKER_00]: You can go through it, while it's still present, and then see that it actually requires things to be mine, in order for it... and then, already, you stop regarding it as self, or, certainly, you regard it as less of a self, because now you see, well, it's actually dependent upon something.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not independent, extra-temporal, changeless self, as anybody would call it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, obviously, the same discernment can go further, and then you realize, well, there is no mind if things don't arise beforehand on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the four great elements paired with consciousness, you know, they rise and fall, they come and go, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, and that's that whole thing, that whole movement, that whole phenomena, is the necessary prerequisite that's simultaneously present with... for the appropriation of
[SPEAKER_00]: of things, for that notion of mind, which is then simultaneously present again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could say, it's because of the appropriation of these things that arise randomly, there is self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to necessarily talk about mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, once you start looking at it, you realize, yeah, it's a sort of a refined way of taking things to be self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just regarding it as mind, but that that's what precedes the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it needs to be done in that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, that which was taken to be itself, that which was the self, will become not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it might still be there, whatever that thing was, whatever that notion of self was.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it was implying stays, but ceases to be yours, because really, you abandon the ownership, only the ownership of that phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have not been negating or denying the whole phenomenon, or trying to reverse engineer or kind of re-explain it in more pleasing terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's true.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because things are taken in mind, sense of self exists, but that can be seen rightly only through the existing sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, when, let's say, one is trying to do mindful thinking, so to say, proper thinking, basically, you're saying that one has to become, let's say, reflexively aware of oneself first, within the situation, then everything starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within the experience as a whole, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can also, because sometimes, if the mindfulness is not developed properly, that sense of self remains kind of under
[SPEAKER_00]: Cloud, that sort of nature of an extra-temporal, changeless, it's everywhere and nowhere, and you can't quite grasp it, because you're trying to grasp it, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you're just mindful of the experience as a whole, of your situation, and then, no matter how ambiguous that sense of self is, it can be designated as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might not be able to grasp it as a fully actual thing, but you can certainly designate it as an ambiguous sense, vague, vague, remote sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the truly extra-temporal, changeless self that exists outside of your experience, you could not conceive it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just could not talk about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't think it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you can do all those things means, no, it's very much within that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, it presents itself as the owner who is outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you believe that presentation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a... that's a self-abuse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just a gratuitous belief, taking it at face value of its presentation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm independent, but you are within the dependent experience, so how can you be independent?
[SPEAKER_00]: And by not dwelling on that, huh, how can you be independent long enough, people end up assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or carrying on that assumption that has been established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just completely gratuitously, no reason for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the reason for it is not thinking about it properly enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you don't think about something often enough, means you're ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why ignorance is absolutely the first cause.
[SPEAKER_01]: I moved on from there, kind of thinking about...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: None of that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that which appears as not changing, you know, experience,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it can only be known as such in relation to that which is changing, which means it's not independent of it, which means then there might be something else in relation to that that's even less changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, from that point of view, that which was unchangeable is actually changing, just at a slower rate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's changing slower than other fast things around you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just how things work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just when when that
[SPEAKER_00]: When that sort of confuses people into believing, ah, this is, this is permanent, because it's not changing as much as other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But whether it's changing, whether at a higher speed or a lower, it's changing very slowly, change is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, this paragraph, I'm not reading the whole thing, I'm just kind of paraphrasing, basically just me trying to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Understand the idea that we were just speaking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: How, like, the positive seems to emanate from some source unseen.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing that was confusing me, as I was reading through the note, was that he mentions that one sutta where he talks about consciousness as arrived at merit, arrived at demerit, arrived at the imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember that one?
[SPEAKER_01]: I get caught up when we start saying, like, consciousness of doing things, like, arrived at, or growing, or other such terms.
Like, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't quite understand what is meant by that, you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could say it like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't think about it that it's... it's doing itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Think about it, it's happening to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you could say that plants are growing by themselves, but I can still induce the notion of, oh, it's doing it by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's basically, yeah, you put a sort of a block of butter in the sun and it will melt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So once there are certain conditions come along, something will happen to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the actions are rooted in wholesome, consciousness arrives at merit.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the action it arrives at demerit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't do... it just
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what ends up being for it, or happening to it, as a result of the conditions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I say, it cognizes a meritorious... Yeah, yeah, it arrives at it, but it's not doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, consciousness grows, because there are directions of growth that bring it towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's just growing, because there is an opening for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that's not there, or that opening is understood, then it won't grow anymore, much in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's happening because the conditions are there, and whatever is positive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, like, I would say, like, our consciousness is out there with the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean it's out there next, like, literally, as matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But means, it's actually, its nature is closer to that which you think is the nature of matter, than it's the nature of what you think yourself is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because consciousness is always assumed as the most personal thing, as the center of experience, to the point that scientists, in inverted commas, found the center of your consciousness, and things like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, all of those sort of silly things, basically, are the result of the view, of that self-centered view, of self and consciousness being the very kind of root of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you start thinking about consciousness in the same independent manner as you're thinking about the four great elements, then things will make more sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's it's on the level of the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they just arise when there is a footing for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness grows when there is an opening for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then your experience, as a whole, is just the result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the whole appropriation of it is completely unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when you refer to the regarding things as mind and the sense of self as a parasite upon the upon the structure that does not require it at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's actually no room for appropriation at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not knowing that, you put it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you're responsible for its existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you're responsible for anything that happens in the time of that fully assumed existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, it's important to recognize that that's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't recognize that as a starting point, then you will say, oh, this is not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reality of things is really pure.
[SPEAKER_00]: The reality of things is nibbāna, and our ignorance is just delusion, which is not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be a true statement if there was the discernible beginning for ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there was a first point, before which things are not ignorant, then develop ignorance, I can say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whenever you look, however you look, whatever you look, you're going to look with your ignorance, which means that is your starting point, that mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because it's a mistake, because it's not supposed to be there, that's why arahantship is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nibbāna is present in everyone's experience as possibility, as a possibility, but not as the ultimate reality, uh, that you sort of achieve just by denying your mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you deny your mistake, and that's a mistake, through your mistake, through your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the beginning one star with one center self is, in a sense,
[SPEAKER_01]: Starting with one's ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's not that you find a way out of ignorance, left or right from ignorance, or above or below.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's right through, while ignorance is still present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The recognition of I am, sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, through that, you can abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing I was, I guess you'd say, excited about, and I'll set the right terms, I had always kind of not quite understood what saṅkhara, pañca, viññāṇa meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, oh, like, oh, yeah, because there's a termination, there's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I kind of had an idea that I think connect... hopefully connected something I wanted to read.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I read the passage?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I wrote viññāṇa being the fundamental determination in that things must be present before anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends on the fact that there is determination at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the the term I made was like determinationism.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like determinism.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you explain or rather how would you describe then the nature of determinationism?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would you describe it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the most fundamental sort of nature of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's in common to every determinationism?
[SPEAKER_00]: In Determinationism, there's to be two things present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it cannot be by itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it cannot be one, just me, it cannot be self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what the nature of self is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's because there are already two, means that nature of determination is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there has to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: There have to be two things simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: And consciousness, being the most fundamental one of them, means it requires the other one, which is matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because consciousness cannot stay stand-alone, that's why it's sort of subordinate to the nature of determination, the nature of having two things bound together.
[SPEAKER_00]: And none of them can be the first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, saṅkhara, pañca, viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how consciousness originates, as defined consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not the other thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's basically the conclusion that I got to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the fact that there is determinationism, okay, where it just works for me, is why consciousness can be at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, it just would be, well, entirely incongruentable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, like... You couldn't look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Purely positive, what does that all mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You couldn't reflect onto it, if there's only one thing present.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no reference point for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why even the nature of the self
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in its heart.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an absolute contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: There can't be one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wrote once, like, perceptions of unity, so to say, are what keep the self alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't possibly conceive unity without having diversity.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's then united.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then your point of view cannot be united with it, because if you were, you wouldn't be aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So consciousness is that sort of
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature, just presence of consciousness and the non-consciousness, the two simultaneous things, means there's always a point of view, which means you cannot be that thing you're having a view of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why even if you witness the unity, you are not part of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you truly become part of unity, it means you become completely unaware.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what kind of notion of unity is that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize any notions of unity that you can have, even in your imagination, will be fully based upon diversity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some mystics might say pure unawareness is something to look for.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but even that, they can develop that notion only based on diversity, which means, well, it can't be than pure unity, because it's diversified.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just, it's complete contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can never be so surmounted by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and I was quite happy to start getting an inkling of what that actually referred to.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was cool.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it is quite important, because
[SPEAKER_00]: Most of people, no matter, you know, some people might press it far enough in terms of the kind of detailed understanding, some people might not go into so much detail, but it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, most of them would assume, all of them, really, assume consciousness in one form or the other, as that kind of internal mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And often it's hard to sort of pin it down or understand it or clarify
[SPEAKER_00]: So that you can actually see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, actually, no, even that, when I, in passing, in careless thinking, regard, oh, my consciousness, or this, or rather, just consciousness already implies mind for most of the people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if you were to clarify it enough, then you stop doing even that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was in one of the letters, early, early letters, and, you know, he mentioned that, and he was talking about consciousness, and he was, he was often quoting Sartre, and so on, and then he, in one of the letters, he kind of realized, oh, actually, no, I think, I think,
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I've been fully, kind of, just...
[SPEAKER_00]: I picked it up from Sartre or something, but I was assuming that Consciousness is always me, as opposed to... or here, as opposed to over there, but Consciousness is on the level of the five aggregates, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, then he realized that, oh, well, if I'm correcting what I just wrote, that means I might have kind of abandoned the view of my Consciousness being myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if that's true, that's very welcome.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the next life, you follow another insight, and another insight, and another insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you build it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like you just started making sense to him, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't like something he took on faith and repeated, repeated, repeated.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess some people could perhaps just take something on faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, whether you take it on faith, or whether you can approach it with sort of critical reflection, and so on,
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to arrive at the same point, which is to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, often people are too lazy, mentally, to make the effort to understand things.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say, oh, I'm not that type.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm kind of the faith type, or sādhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: I follow sādhā and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you still making effort to understand through your faith?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize most of them don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether it's faith, whether it's intellectual understanding, it needs to be... needs to lead you to the understanding of the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for Yanavira, it was not faith, for sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was basically just trying to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like an insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was after insight, upon insight, upon insight, things were getting clearer.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, for those people, too, they kind of mix up the fact that even someone whom there is a wisdom type has to have faith, still.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of them don't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had, clearly, he had faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, he wouldn't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was trying to understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he had faith that that was right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he wasn't sure until he understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, it's not like you suddenly get the knowledge of everything and all at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a build-up, sort of, of overcoming and, sort of, failing out that assumption, just sort of destroying it bit by bit by bit, weakening it, and then things become clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, once it's clear, you can't revert back.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, well, you were never supposed to have those assumptions, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experience did not require them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experience did not induce their assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Experience was not responsible for any assumption at all, in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was responsible is you not understanding experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now that you have understood the experience, the result of that is cessation of assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now that you have understood it, you cannot un-understand it and then bring back the assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the point is,
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the end, if you read the suttas, you'll see whatever different approach the Buddha might have taken, it all leads to full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what makes an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not some perfect adherence to this method, or to that method, or to this mantra.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's full understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you understand things when you fully know them, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other way to describe it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, as I said, it cannot be reverted back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I have to even admit that, up until fairly recently, there was this, I think, big, subtle notion of what you described as ignorance, as this mystical entity, as opposed to an active thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's an active, passive ignoring, sorry, ignoring of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I just said five minutes ago, like, yeah, because you don't look at it often enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's automatically a form of ignoring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Compare that with following distractions of the senses, adhering to the view because they please you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you kind of reinforce the act of not looking at those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you reinforce your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, that was very important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I remember when I kind of realized that, because, yeah, everybody starts with the assumption of ignorance is kind of buried deep down inside, under all this kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's the most...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the thing on top of, like, on the very surface of everything what you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's right there and you carry it throughout your, what, lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's because it's so close to your eyes, basically, you don't see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because eyes just always look beyond and other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why distraction takes you away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you look at it, it's it's it's really just a fully an active attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's sort of active in the sense you engage in it, but you can engage in passively.
[SPEAKER_00]: That already constitutes an active attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no effort, ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it maintains so easily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Flawless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Flawless maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, using all these kinds of like the things you've been talking about, I think I understood...
[SPEAKER_01]: I remember one time, I think it may be like July, August, I brought you that sutta where it talks about like feeling as a bubble, matter as a lump of salt.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went back to the magic show one, and I, I don't know, I just wanted to share it with you, see what you think.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I wrote, a magic show always involves deception.
[SPEAKER_01]: A card trick, for example, relies on the viewer not seeing, or being ignorant of, the hidden card of the magician's sleep.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha compares consciousness to a magic show.
[SPEAKER_01]: The indications generated by consciousness's denial of the positive, when not understood, point to the self superimposed upon negative, rather than simply pointing to a negative necessary structural aspect, not seeing this and quote-unquote illusions, real as such, of self as master appears.
This self can, in a sense, appear both positive and negative.
We talked about that stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can speak of myself as an arisen phenomena in some sense, but also as that behind the direction disclosed by consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Since this is all assumed as valid, self is assumed to be independent of either positive or negative, since it is seen or assumed to be
[SPEAKER_01]: can be both for the experience as a whole, because one fails to see that wherever self may seem to go, positive and negatives determine each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whichever location one assumes, becomes a moon point, because they're all undermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it was just interesting how this one thought, and then that sutta comes on, like, oh yeah, about that one, you kind of just think, like, it kind of makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a deception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, think of that deception equals a parasite, in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not... Samādhi and things that are being, sort of, hidden by that deception, have nothing to do with deception.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't care about deception.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the viewer who's deceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things remain unaffected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cards don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you use them for deception or not, they remain different to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, the organism, so there's a parasitic, they're not aware, it just doesn't affect them, it affects the viewer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, that's the starting point, because there is no first moment when that parasite or that deception begun.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because that's the starting point, it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although that being is fully, kind of,
[SPEAKER_00]: Given to it through that assumption, through that mistake, through that deception, through that parasite, it is real, it is given as such, and it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, only through admitting that it's real, we can go through it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, again, it won't be... it won't become unreal.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will basically become not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it becomes not mine, then the main fuel of deception ceases, and then it's, well, not real in a sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it's there, it's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important thing to recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: When people say things are not real, eh... when people say things are not real, they fail to see that that requires those things to be present there, in order for them to be designated as unreal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wrote an illusion in the print.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, yeah, I don't think you think that, but I'm just saying you have to be careful, because you can still fall into, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Subtler assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of unreal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, it's not unreal.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unreal and it's real as unreal deception.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mirage, the magic trick, it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's hard, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's a good example.
[SPEAKER_00]: The people misunderstand.
[SPEAKER_00]: They use the example just to justify, ah, it's not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they fail to see that you're witnessing a magic trick and it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't pin it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it's real as a trick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you understand it, once you see what he done, he pulled the card out of his sleeve, the whole thing is now revealed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still the same thing, same performance, same everything, but it's not a trick anymore, because it has been understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the being of it as a trick has ceased, because it's seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, see, that's already slightly sucked away, to kind of understand, and then to just say, ah, it's not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's real is what's behind the trick, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how people who dismiss the whole, the whole experience often.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I see what you're saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the hidden reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's basically the same reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's your attitude that changes the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Reality remains unaffected.
[SPEAKER_00]: The magician still continues performing the same trick and deceiving probably the rest of the audience, but you've seen through it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're witnessing the exactly same things that you've been witnessing before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, your mind is not deceived in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, nothing has really changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's somebody who's fully understood the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not deceived anymore in regard to everything that has stayed the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people can't tell the other ones apart, externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything can stay the same.